<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of Lieut. Gen. Cromwell, and Com. Gen. Ireton, against the scandalous aspersions cast upon them in a posted libell signed by one Tompson. And likewise a true state of the case concerning the said Tompson. / By A.C.</title>
            <author>A. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78252</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E431_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206102</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865287</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865287</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161505</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78252)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161505)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 68:E431[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of Lieut. Gen. Cromwell, and Com. Gen. Ireton, against the scandalous aspersions cast upon them in a posted libell signed by one Tompson. And likewise a true state of the case concerning the said Tompson. / By A.C.</title>
                  <author>A. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Laurence Chapman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647 [i.e. 1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireton, John, --  Sir, 1615-1690 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thompson, William, d. 1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Military offenses --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161505:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A VINDICATION <hi>OF</hi> Lieut. Gen. Cromwell, AND Com. Gen. Ireton, Againſt the ſcandalous aſperſions caſt upon them in a Poſted LIBELL ſigned by one <hi>TOMPSON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And likewiſe a true ſtate of the Caſe concerning the ſaid <hi>TOMPSON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>A. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>march .7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
               </add> 
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Laurence Chapman.</hi> 1647.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:161505:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161505:2"/>
            <head>A Vindication of Lieu. Gen. <hi>Cromwell</hi> and Com. Gen. <hi>Ireton,</hi> againſt a poſted Libell ſigned by one TOMPSON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Tompſon</hi> being a Corporall of Capt. <hi>Pitchfords</hi> Troop in Col. <hi>Whaleys</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, about five moneths agoe was with ſome idle company at a Taverne in the Town where that Troop quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered; where in drinking and gaming late in the night he fell into a drunken quarrell with ſome of the company about ſome money they were at play for; and the Miſtris of the houſe with ſome of the ſervants endeavouring to part them, he kickt her on the face, kickt and beat ſome of the ſervants, and then clamorouſly charging her and them that they had feloniouſly pickt 20 li. out of his pocket, he went and fetcht his ſword, with ſome other of his comrades, and with his ſword drawn fell upon the houſhold, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded three of them, chaſed away the reſt, drove the Miſtris of the houſe into a chamber for ſhelter, ſeized upon one of the ſervants and took him priſoner away with him, threatning him to tie him neck and heeles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161505:3"/> together, with other terrible threats and ourages to the family. Hereupon being complained of to the Regimentall counſell of that Regiment, he (at laſt) confeſt before the Councell, that his clamour of 20 li. taken from him was but a pretence, and that it was not really done to him: The reſt of the abuſes and outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were fully proved againſt him, and to all or moſt of them himſelfe confeſſed. For theſe and the like matters of Brawling and Baratry he was cenſured by that Councell (with ſomething of reparation to the family) to be caſhierrd the Regiment at the head of it the next Randezvouz; but at their next Randezvouz (through ſome neglect or other) being not brought forth, the ſentence of caſhiering was not formally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted upon him, onely he was put out of the muſter, and the Regiment-marſhall ſoon after was ordered by the Major to diſcharge him from the Regiment. But he taking occaſion and encouragement from the muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous diſtempers then wrought or endeavoured in the Army by the London-agents and their partakers, cloſed in with them, and took the boldneſſe reſolutely to continue with the Troop and Regiment, to march and take quarter with them in deſpight of the Officers; which accordingly he did, endeavouring to enflame diſcontents and diſtractions amongſt them, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for the ſame purpoſe imployed himſelfe as an Agent in the name of that Regiment to other Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Army: In which he endeavoured and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered to raiſe great diſturbances.</p>
            <p>Afterwards there being another Rendezvouz of that Regiment he came thither with the Troop, obtruding himſelfe in deſpight and contempt of the Officers to be and act in the place from which he was caſhiered, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161505:3"/> at the Rendezvouz the Officers requiring his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (as being caſhiered) he refuſed to ſubmit to that cenſure, making clamorous out-cries to the ſouldiers, That the Regimentall Councell had proceeded ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally againſt him. To which the Officers replied, That if he thought they had wronged him, he might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine to the Generall and Councell of war at the head quarter, and there the matter being re-examined he might have reparation if cauſe appeared. But that alſo he refuſed, crying but, That he could expect no juſtice there, but he would and did appeale to the Regiment; And by ſuch mutinous outcries he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, and did endanger a great mutiny and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in the Regiment, but the Officers with much a do pacified them for that time: After which he would needs continue to march and take free quarter with the Troop, and endevoured to raiſe further mutines, and diſturbances in the Troop and Regiment, and in other Regiments of the Army; untill at laſt the Colonell or Major cauſed him againe to be apprehended and ſent to the head quarter (then at <hi>Windſor)</hi> where he was for theſe things committed Priſoner to the Marſhall Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, to be tryed for the ſame by the Councell of War there. But being brought before the Councell, and charged with theſe things, he refuſed to anſwer them, pleading that he was caſhiered, and ſo being no Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that Councell had nothing to doe with him; and this he did with very inſolent and contemptuous language and carriage to the Court: The Councell neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thought fit to proceed againſt him, either as a Souldier (if the ſentence of caſhiering were not exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted upon him) or (if it were) then as one pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be a Souldier, and obtruding himſelf into the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161505:4"/> Army, to be and act as a Souldier, without being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled in ſome Troop or Company, by the government whereof he might be kept in order (againſt which ſort of perſons the Articles of Warre (made lawes by the authority of Parliament,) doe expreſſely provide and authorize the Court Marſhall, to proceed as well as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt offending Souldiers:) But the proceeding to Judgement upon him, being ſuſpended (while ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examinations were to be taken) and he ordered to be continued Priſoner that while in the Marſhall's cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody; during this ſuſpence, coming to Lievtenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Cromwell</hi> with pretences of extreame neceſſity, about ſome occaſions of his own to go to <hi>London,</hi> and promiſing faithfully to render himſelfe againe into the Marſhall's hands within a few days limitted, he obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed leave of the Lievtenant Generall to goe upon his parole. But inſtead of rendring himſelfe againe a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner into the Marſhall's hands, he ſent to the Generall, and Councell a Declaration and Proteſtation againſt them, (which it ſeemes his buſineſſe at <hi>London,</hi> was to get drawne and Printed,) wherein after much revileing and tedious diſputes againſt all power of the Court Martiall, and all exerciſe of Military diſcipline, either upon Souldiers or others, except in Actuall warre, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be expreſſely authoriſed by Parliament, and limited by certain laws, for the reſtraining of diſorders and abuſes amongſt the Souldiery) he concludes with a proteſtation againſt the Councell of War, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Robbers, Theeves, and Murtherers; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that if they ſhould any further meddle with him, he would raiſe the Hue and Cry of the Kingdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them as ſuch, and would endevour by all meanes in the world to deſtroy them, or to that effect.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:161505:4"/>
            <p> Since this (it ſeemes) he hath continued about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and (as is informed) hath been frequently amongſt the Souldiers about <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> endevouring to ſtirre up mutinous diſtempers amongſt them; untill on Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday laſt, the Lievetenant Generall, and Commiſſary Generall, going from the Houſe of Commons, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Generall upon a Councell of Warre at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> and meeting this <hi>Tompſon</hi> as they came out (know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was duly a Priſoner to the Marſhall Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as aforeſaid; but falſefying his parole, had never ſince rendred himſelf into the Marſhall's hands accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it,) They charged two Souldiers with him, and immediately appointed an Enſigne of the Guard, to ſee him brought before the Generall at <hi>White-hall,</hi> where by his Excellencie's appointment, the Marſhal Generall did reſume him into his cuſtody, to be tryed by the Councell of Warre, upon thoſe things for which he was formerly committed. And this is all that grand violation to the Rights and Liberties of the free Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England,</hi> for which the Lievtenant Generall, and Commiſſary Generall were (in that <hi>Tompſons</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe) poſted up the other day, about the Towne in Printed Tickets, whereby (in ſtead of the Hue and Cry, threatned in his Proteſtation) an Alarm was given to the people, as if the eſtates, liberties, and lives of all the free commons of <hi>England</hi> were at one ſtroke, ready to be deſtroyed in him. But what protection to their liberties, eſtates, or lives, againſt the violences of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, or others the poore Commons might expect from this fellow and others, of his temper (though zealous p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etenders for the ſame) if their licentious humor ſhould prevaile, men may take a meaſure by thoſe abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and outrages, and violences done to the poore
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161505:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> people, for which this fellow was firſt complain'd of and cenſur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d, and upon cenſure for which, all his later clamors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> out-cries, and mutinous practiſes have enſued. From which and other l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke inſtances it may juſtly be doubted, that this fellow and ſuch as he, would faine be ſuch free Commoners, as to communicate freely of what any other man hath, and to ſay or doe freely what they will and can againſt any man without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule for it, and till then will never thinke themſelves in the full ſtate of free-commoner-ſhip.</p>
            <p>If any doe doubt the truth of the cauſes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt this man (as they are before alledged) they may ſee them at large (with much advantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove what's here expreſt) as they are upon Record, in the hands of the Judge Advocate at <hi>White-hall;</hi> where and from whom alſo they may underſtand the later p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oceedings of the Generall, and Councell of Warre againſt him on Wedneſday laſt, in the tryall and juſt condemnation of him, together with the grounds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as alſo his unparallel'd inſolent, contemptuous, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumeliou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and menacing carriage againſt the Generall a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d whole Councell at his tryall, not becoming a Chriſtian or a civill man.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gilb. Mabbett.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
